Amit Kumar Singh

Fullstack Developer * DevOps

Ranchi, Jharkahnd (+91) 82100-98916 amitsin6h@gmail.com.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/amitsin6h/ https://github.com/amitsin6h

Self-taught computer programmer. Currently Founder, Fullstack Developer & DevOps in start-up Devconsole. I have 2.5+ years of experience specializing in backend/infrastructure, web development and security. I love to share my programming knowledge with the students. A super nerd who loves Linux and enjoys to customize all of the development environment. Interested in devising a better problem-solving method for challenging tasks, and learning new technologies and tools if the need arises.

Work Experience

Founder, Fullstack Developer

Jan 2019 - Present

Feelin

V2.1.0 - V3.0.0

- Updated the complete UI/UX of the app using React Native, and other third-party libraries
- Updated the backend using Apollo, Graphql, Express
- Designed the product website using MERN stack
- Implemented Redis caching technique
- Updated MongoDB schema for the product
- Built and deployed overall service infrastructure utilizing Docker containers.

V1.0.0 - 2.1.0

- Developed the complete UI/UX of the product using React Native and other third party libraries
- Designed the product website using HTML, CSS, and other javascript libraries.
- Implemented RESTful API server using Expressis and Nodejs
- Implemented API request validation using
- Implemented API caching technique to handle
- Implemented Flynn PaaS to manage product on
- Implemented Git for the project
- Designed advance schema for the complete product
- Built and deployed overall service infrastructure utilizing Docker container, Flynn PaaS(Opensource focusing on high-availability, fault tolerance, and auto-scaling

Open Source Contributor

Mar 2019 - May 2019

GirlScript Summer of Code

MEVN CLI: A CLI tool for getting started with the MEVN stack. It offers a super-simple boilerplate template and additional utilities for building a MEVN stack-based web app.

Education

MBA, IT & Systems

2019 - 2021

IMS, Ranchi University

 Selected for "Business English for Young Professional Workshop" conducted by U.S Embassy

BBA, Marketing

2015 - 2018

Marwari College, Ranchi University

AISSCE, Commerce

2013 - 2015

2013

Central Academy, Bariatu

AISSEArmy Public School, Ranchi

 Completed 2 years (2010-2012) in Army wing 3JH BN NCC Ranchi as Lance Corporal/ Corporal. Also cleared 'A' Certificate examination held in 2012 under the authority of Ministry of Defence, Government of India

Hackathons & Achievements

- 2020, **eLife Innovation Leader**, eLife
- 2019, Intel Edge Al Scholar, Udacity
- 3019, Y Combinator Startup School
- 2018, OpenTechNights Winner, FOSSASIA
- 2017, Quality Assurance Contributor, Mozilla
- 2017, **First**, Hackathon De Corps
- 2016, **Second**, UTKRAANTI'16 with Padarth'16 IIT Bombay
- 2016, **Assocaate Trainer**, App Development Training for Nepalese
- 2015, Top 10, App Hackathon (Gov. of Jharkhand)

Founder, Fullstack Developer

Ian 2018 - Nov 2018

Devconsole

- Developed the complete UI/UX of the product
- Designed the REST API server using Expressis and Nodeis
- Implemented API request validation using
- Designed MongoDB schema for the complete product
- Built and deployed overall service infrastructure utilizing Docker container, Flynn PaaS

Research Intern

Jun 2018 - Jul 2018

LinuxWorld Informatics Pvt Ltd

- SAAS(Software As A Service) A one-click implementation
 was achieved which provided the clients Firefox browser
 and VLC media player software's on their systems from
 DOCKERS running on the cloud server.
- STAAS(Storage As A Service)
 - Block Storage In Block storage we used ISCSI Protocol to provide clients with block storage available at the cloud to be used at the client system.
 - Object Storage In Object storage, using NFS and SSHFS Protocol to provide user fixed storage overcloud.
- CAAS(Container As A Service) A one-click launch, starting, stopping and removing and providing the terminal of docker container was achieved.
- **PAAS(Platform As A Service)** A one-click launch of python platform was provided for clients where they can code as they wish.
- **Hadoop** A CGI based web portal was developed for a one-click setup of hdfs and map-reduce cluster depending on the requirements of the client per se, the size of the cluster required, and the number of processors required for the big data analysis.
- Machine Learning The web service for the client was secured by Face recognition using machine learning and also include parts of speech recognition using python modules. IMAGE PROCESSING constitutes a large portion of the security aspect of the service.
- Ansible The entire configuration requirement of the project was met by the creation of ANSIBLE playbooks for both the client and the cloud.
- Dockers For the safe and secure single client-based service production, most of the services were provided through dockers only

Skills

- Front-End: HTML5, CSS3, JS, JQuery, Bootstrap, AngularJS, ReactJS, React Native, Redux, SocketIO
- Back-End: NodeJS, GraphQL, Apollo, Python, PHP, SocketIO
- Web Server: Nginx, Apache
- Mobile App: React-Native, Android Studio, Ionic,
- **Desktop App:** NW.js
- Database: NoSql, MySQL
- Web Framework: MERN Stack, MEAN Stack, Django, Flask, Codelgniter, LAMP
- Programming Languages: Python, JavaScript, PHP
- Version Control Tools: Git, Github, Bitbucket
- PaaS: CloudJiffy, Dokku, Flynn
- **DevOps:** Ansible, Splunk
- Big Data: Hadoop, Hive, Spark, Splunk
- Data Analysis: Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plottly
- Others: Web Security, OWASP TOP 10, Networking, Web Scrapping, Linux, Quality Assurance, Data Mining

Certifications

- 2019, cloudyBoss accreditation cBX82 Technology
- 2017, Red Hat Certified System Administrator
- 2017, Red Hat Certified Specialist in Ansible Automation
- 2016, Intro to Python for Data Science, DataCamp

Projects

Devconsole - An online student and startup platform

Al Monkey - Al based web browser which consult user based on their search query

MozCode Paste - This project aims to paste code, share code and get the code reviewed. This project was shortlisted for Mozilla Pulse

Air Notes - Notes app in which notes can be synced online

UC News Clone - A clone of UC News app which shows news from diffrent news website.

Django Twitter - Twitter clone using python and django web framework

Digital Marketing Intern

lan 2018 - Feb 2018

Genesis Digisec

- Developed complete SEO and Google analytics for a wordpress website, also worked in UI/UX of the website
- Suggested online marketing strategy for the promotion of the website

Jr. Researcher

Feb 2017 - Aug 2017

Cyber Peace Foundation

- Worked in Indian Honeynet Project
- Invloved some website and web application related projects
- Developed windows and Linux software using NodeWebkit

Software Developer

Nov 2016 - Feb 2017

ResultsTrack Pvt. Ltd

- Involved in Data Visualization and Data Analysis projects, alon with some websites and web application projects
- Created an android app to collect survey in offline mode and automatically gets updated whenever the internet was connected

Intern

Aug 2016 - Nov 2016

Nathcorp Inc

• Involved in Data Visualization and Data Analysis projects and worked in dynamic graphs and maps using php and third party javascript library

Volunteer

Code Contributor

OpenGenus

 Code contribution for different algorithms in Cosmos. Suggested idea and worked on mockup of Cosmos Code Compiler (C3)

Code Contributor

PyCon India 2017

- Working with web development team for fixing the web related issues
- Volunteered for Machine Learning Fruitful and Fun using Orange talk

Code Contributor

PyConf Hyderabad 2017

 Working with web development team for code contribution to website and invloved in fixing web related issues in github

Club Leader

HackClub

 Responsible for building local community of developers in college and universities and organizing meet-ups

Mozillian

Mozilla

- Responsible for event organizing, meet-ups for community and create FOSS Awareness in colleges, schools and universities
- Quality Assurance contributor from Mozilla India team